Finding Aid to the People vs. Owen Bathhouse Closure Litigation Records, 1984-1987
San Francisco History Center, San Francisco Public Library
People vs. Owen Bathhouse Closure Litigation Records
1984-1987
SFH 31
San Francisco (Calif.). Bureau of Communicable Disease Control.
1 carton (1.0 cubic feet)
San Francisco History Center, San Francisco Public Library 100 Larkin Street San Francisco, CA, 94102 (415) 557-4567 info@sfpl.org
Court documents and other records related to the case People of the State of California, ex rel. George Agnost, et al. vs. Ima Jean Owen, et al. (Superior Court No. 830-321), aka People vs. Owen, filed October 10, 1984, by San Francisco City Attorney George Agnost and Director of Public Health Mervyn Silverman, in an effort to close fourteen bathhouses, sex clubs, bookstores, and adult movie theaters by claiming them to be a public nuisance, in response to the burgeoning AIDS epidemic.
Access
The collection is open for research. Please call the San Francisco History Center for hours and information at 415-557-4567.
Four confidential documents written between City Attorneys and Department of Public Health officials are restricted from public access.
Provenance
The collection was acquired via an anonymous donation December 18, 1996.
Related Archival Materials
Researchers are encouraged to see also AIDS Office of the San Francisco Department of Public Health Records, 1982-1994 (SFH 4).
Related Publications
Researchers are encouraged to see also "The San Francisco Bathhouse Battles of 1984: Civil Liberties, AIDS Risk, and Shifts in Health Policy." Disman, Christopher. Co-published simultaneously in Journal of Homosexuality, (Harrington Park Press, an imprint of The Haworth Press, Inc.) Vol. 44, Nos. ¾, 2003, pp. 71-129; and Gay Bathhouses and Public Health Policy, (ed. William J. Woods and Diane Binson) Harrington Park Press, an imprint of The Haworth Press, Inc., 2003, pp. 71-129.
Biographical/Historical note
The court case People of the State of California, ex rel. George Agnost, et al. vs. Ima Jean Owen, et al. (Superior Court No. 830-321), aka People vs. Owen, filed Oct. 10, 1984 by San Francisco City Attorney George Agnost and Director of Public Health Mervyn Silverman, documents the efforts of the San Francisco Department of Public Health to close fourteen bathhouses, sex clubs, bookstores, and adult movie theaters by claiming them to be a public nuisance, as a response to the then-new knowledge of sexual methods of AIDS transmission. More broadly, the case positions San Francisco in a local and ultimately national public debate over AIDS–related policies in the 1980s, in which city officials, community activists, and private citizens struggle with the relationship between public health and gay civil rights.
Defendant businesses in the original Oct. 10 complaint were: The Academy; The Animals; The Boot Camp; Club Baths of San Francisco; California Baths Corp.; Club San Francisco; Folsom Gulch Books; Gartman Enterprises; Jack's Turkish Baths; Jaguar Book Store; The Savages Theater; San Francisco Health Club; Tea Room Theater; The Slot Hotel; The Baths.
Although the provenance of this collection is unknown, based on the organization and original notations on the material, the records appear to be from the files of Dean Echenberg, then-Director of the Bureau of Communicable Disease Control, of the San Francisco Department of Public Health.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the material consists of copies of pleadings filed by both plaintiffs and defendants, including declarations of physicians, public health experts, and investigators, upon which the City based its application for a temporary restraining order, preliminary injunction, and permanent injunction to enforce Dr. Silverman's closure order of Oct. 9, 1984; along with subsequent court filings, including writs of supersedeas, a summons, the modified preliminary injunction, depositions, supplemental declarations, exhibits, and a defendants' first set of interrogatories. There is also some case-related correspondence, including letters, memos, articles, and investigative reports, between city officials, law firms, private investigators, and community organizations. Some correspondence concerns proposed legislation to transfer jurisdiction for bathhouses from the Police Code to the Health Code.
The declarations in support of the bathhouse closures are of particular interest, as they reflect a representative set of medical and official points of view on businesses that facilitate public gay sex and the relationship of these businesses to the spread of AIDS. Declarants include Mervyn Silverman, Director of Public Health (DPH); Dean Echenberg, Director of the Bureau of Communicable Disease Control at DPH; faculty and administrators at University of California, San Francisco (UCSF), San Francisco General Hospital (SFGH), Mount Zion Hospital, the AIDS Activities Office, San Francisco Veterans Administration Medical Center, California State Department of Health Services, the Center for Disease Control; and several private investigators.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1. Sex clubs/Bathhouses Subject Files, 1984-1986; Series 2. Court documents, 1984-1987. Series 2 is arranged chronologically.
San Francisco (Calif.). Bureau of Communicable Disease Control. -- Archives; AIDS (Disease)--California--San Francisco--History; AIDS (Disease)--Epidemiology; AIDS (Disease)--Government policy--California--San Francisco; AIDS (Disease)--Political aspects; Civil court records; Gay bathhouses--California--San Francisco.; Gay men--Sexual behavior--Government policy--California--San Francisco.; Echenberg, Dean Fredric
- Sex Clubs/Bathhouses Subject Files, 1984-1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Court Documents, 1984-1987; Series 2
  Scope and Contents
  Copies of court documents from People vs. Owen, with a small amount of interfiled correspondence and filing notes.
  - Summons to Jaguar Book Store, October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Complaint for permanent injunction, preliminary injunction and temporary restraining order, October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Declarations in support of application for preliminary injunction and temporary restraining order (Vol. I, Silverman-Conant), October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Declarations in support of application for preliminary injunction and temporary restraining order (Vol. I, Volberding-Goldsmith), October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Declarations in support of application for preliminary injunction and for temporary restraining order (Vol. II), October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Declaration of Dr. Dean Echenberg, October 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Order to show cause re preliminary injunction, October 16, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Petition for writ of supersedeas after grant of temporary restraining order, October 16, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Exhibits to petition for writ of supersedeas, October 16, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notice of taking deposition and request for production of documents, October 24, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notice of taking deposition records only, October 24, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deposition of Dean F. Echenberg, M.D., October 29, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Declarations in support of opposition to preliminary injunction, November 6, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Supplemental declaration of Dean Echenberg, November 9, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Supplemental declaration of Mervyn Silverman, November 14, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to issuance of preliminary injunction, November 14, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Preliminary injunction, November 28, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Modified preliminary injunction, December 21, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Petition for a writ of supersedeas after grant of modified preliminary injunction, June 3, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Discovery requests from bathhouse operators, with accompanying letter from City Attorney George Agnost and Chief Trial Deputy Philip S. Ward to Dean Echenberg, June 21, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Court documents re: motion for further modification of preliminary injunction, March 4, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Investigative report and court documents re: order to show cause re: contempt, April 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Memorandum of points and authorities in support of order to show cause re contempt, with copy of modified preliminary injunction, May 4, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)